Guide to the Joel Garreau Papers, 1954-1994
George Mason University Libraries
- Series 1: Edge City, 1959-February 1994
  - Subseries 1.1:Shadow Governments, October 1976-January 1991
    - Shadow Government Leisure World 2 of 6, December 1990 (Box 28, Folder 13)
      Documents about Leisure World, a planned retirement community in Mesa, AZ. Material includes the December 1990 issue of Leisure News, the 1990 Leisure World Community Telephone Directory and a Leisure World Reality brochure.
    - Shadow Government Leisure World 3 of 6, July 1989-November 1990 (Box 28, Folder 14)
      Documents and correspondence about Leisure World, a planned retirement community in Mesa, AZ. Material includes a map of Leisure World, a sales report, correspondence about Leisure World newspaper publication, highlights of the October 1990 Leisure World board of directors meeting, status of Leisure World districts, July 1990 Monthly activity report for Leisure World, a list of the Leisure World board of directors, an events schedule for Leisure World and the March and July 1990 issues of Leisure News.
    - Shadow Government Leisure World 4 of 6, December 1989-December 1990 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      Documents and correspondence about Leisure World, a planned retirement community in Mesa, AZ. Material includes the August and November 1990 issues of Leisure News, the December 1990 issue of Leisure World News, notes, a letter to advertisers and a copy of a Lease and Publishing agreement between the Leisure World Community Association and Labyrinth Publications.
    - Shadow Government Leisure World 5 of 6, October 1976-February 1988 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      Documents and correspondence about Leisure World, a planned retirement community in Rossmoor, Maryland. Material includes Norman Dreyfuss's IDI-Maryland Inc. business card, notes, results of a resident survey, Leisure World Living a guidebook for residents, an article from Leisure World News "Clubhouse Rules", "Rossmoor Leisure World of Maryland The First Ten Years of a Five Year Plan 1966-1976" by C. Bill Courtright, three issues of Leisure World News from March 1987, four newsletters from Greens II a condominium at Leisure World, The Legal Structure of Leisure World by Mortimer D. Goldstein, Leisure World of Maryland organizational chart, Leisure World Community Corporation Community Council committee lists, a list of requirements and dues to play in golf tournaments and swimming pool charges, a list of community regulations and a poster of newspaper articles about Leisure World Maryland.
    - Shadow Government Leisure World 6 of 6, January 1986-June 1987 (Box 29, Folder 3)
      Documents and correspondence about Leisure World, a planned retirement community in Rossmoor, Maryland. Material includes a book of notes about The Greens a condominium in Leisure World, a publication from International Developers Inc, an International Developers Inc report of company activities, a folder containing press releases and floor plans, a fact sheet about the Greens at Leisure World, press releases, a contact list for Leisure World organizations and activities, a personal biography of Giuseppe Cecchi the president of IDI, the 1986-1987 Leisure World of Maryland community directory, "Rossmoor Leisure World of Maryland The First Ten Years of a Five Year Plan 1966-1976" by C. Bill Courtright, the Greens project report, Richard M. Schultz's Leisure World business card, Annette L. Ruth's Ives and Associates business card, a poster celebrating Leisure World's 20th anniversary, a schedule of events, transcripts of notes, a list of the Tytran board of directors and a promotional folder about The Greens at Leisure World including a list of estimated monthly costs, floor plans and a Washington Post article "The Senior Suburb: Leisure World's Busy Life by Michael Kernan.
    - Leisure World, June 1987 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      Jeanette Manner's Leisure World of Maryland Corp. business card and a note to Garreau about Leisure World. Sources
    - Shadow Government Shirley Swiney Local, March 1987 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      Transcripts of notes about development in the Washington, DC area. Sources
    - Shadow Government Activism Local, April 1989 (Box 29, Folder 6)
      A Washington Post article "Activism Gains in Suburbia" by Stephen C Fehr.
    - Shadow Government Local Kingstowne, November 1988 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      A Washington Post article "New Fairfax Neighborhoods Seek Identity" by Lynda Richardson.
    - Shadow Government Dearborn, Michigan, 1988-November 1990 (Box 29, Folder 8)
      Documents about Dearborn, Michigan. Material includes a Dearborn visitors guide, a pictorial souvenir from the Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village, transcripts of notes, a transcript of an interview between Garreau and David Lewis the University of Michigan historian of the automobile, a transcript of an interview of John Wright the director of the Henry Ford Museum, John Wright's business card, a Dearborn dining guide, a brochure for the Henry Ford estate, a Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village guide and the 1988 and autumn 1990 event guides for the Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village.
    - Shadow Government Local Civil Liberties, November 1989 (Box 29, Folder 9)
      A Washington Post article "The Malling of the Salvation Army" by David Streitfeld.
    - Shadow Government Fairlane, April-December 1990 (Box 29, Folder 10)
      Four issues of Fairlane magazine about Fairlane a planned community in Dearborn, Michigan.
  - Subseries 1.2: Til Hazel, 1959-July 1991
    Material from Joel Garreau's book "Edge City" dealing with John 'Til' Hazel. Featured in Chapter Ten of Edge City, Hazel was a prominent land developer in Northern Virginia. He began his law career by condemning land in Northern Virginia that would be used for the construction of the Capital Beltway. Garreau described his work in Edge City: "For thirty years he had been a key player in the economic and social revolution that culminated with eight Edge Cities blooming in Northern Virginia. One of them, Tysons Corner, drew astounded observers from around the world to its high-rises and intersections."
    - Virginia Businesses, May 1988-March 1989 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Notes, correspondence, contact information and articles about Til Hazel and his work.
    - Virginia Lawyers, 1986-1988 (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Lists and descriptions of Virginia lawyers and law firms.
    - Martindale-Hubbell, 1959-1984 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Notes and lists and descriptions of lawyers and law firms.
    - The Power Elite, January 1989 (Box 30, Folder 4)
      An article about 100 influential people in the Washington, D.C. area featuring Til Hazel.
    - "Earthmover" Til Hazel, July 1991 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      Three copies of an article about Til Hazel's work.
    - Risse, Undated (Box 30, Folder 6)
      Notes about Til Hazel and Ed Risse.
    - Shelly Mastrain, January 1987-January 1990 (Box 30, Folder 7)
      Notes, questionnaires, correspondence, maps, contact lists and other documents from Shelly Mastrain.
    - Virginia Center, January 1986 (Box 30, Folder 8)
      An article about the development of a mized-use complex at the Vienna Metro Station.
    - Tower Club, September-November 1989 (Box 30, Folder 9)
      An article, promotional material, correspondence, and newsletters about the Tycon Tower in Tysons Corner, Virginia.
    - St. Stephen's, July-August 1989 (Box 30, Folder 10)
      Articles about Til Hazel's firm and St. Stephen's church in Alexandria, Virginia. Also included is the St. Stephen's Board of Governors.
    - Power Line Magazine Til Hazel, April 1987-October 1988 (Box 30, Folder 11)
      Articles about Til Hazel's development projects sparking controversy.
    - Proffers, November 1988 (Box 30, Folder 12)
      An article about proffers, "financial agreements negotiated between certain Northern Virginia communities and developers in exchange for the developers being given the right build projects."
    - Til Notes 2/16 Interview, Undated (Box 30, Folder 13)
      Notes from an interview.
    - Hazel-Peterson Developments, July 1985-July 1987 (Box 30, Folder 14)
      Articles about Hazel-Peterson Companies projects. Also included is a promotional publication from Hazel-Peterson Companies.
    - Profile John Herrity, March 1987-May 1989 (Box 30, Folder 15)
      Washington Post articles about John Herrity.
    - Histories Tysons Corner, May 1965-October 1988 (Box 30, Folder 16)
      Articles showing the history of development in Tysons Corner, Virginia. Also included is "From Country Crossroads to Suburban City: The Transformation of Tysons Corner, Virginia" by Shelley S. Mastran.
    - Til, Undated (Box 30, Folder 17)
      Notes about Til Hazel
    - Sidney O. Dewberry, December 1988 (Box 30, Folder 18)
      An article about developer Sidney O. Dewberry and excerpts from a book about Arlington.
    - Burke Centre, January 1978-January 1988 (Box 30, Folder 19)
      An Urban Land Institute project reference file on the Burke Centre in Burke, Virginia. Also included is "New Town Planning and the Garden City/Greenbelt Ideal".
    - GMU Hazel, January 1987-March 1990 (Box 30, Folder 20)
      Articles and correspondence about the growth and expansion of George Mason University.
    - Tysons, September 1989 (Box 30, Folder 21)
      A list of questions for Til Hazel about Tysons Corner, Virginia.
    - The History Miscellaneous Clips, March 1980-January 1984 (Box 30, Folder 22)
      Articles about the law career of Til Hazel.
    - Histories 3 Counties, February 1986-December 1988 (Box 30, Folder 23)
      Articles and notes about the history of development in Montgomery County, Fairfax County, and Prince George's County.
    - History George Mason Clips, December 1974-July 1979 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      Articles about the expansion of George Mason University.
    - Burke Clips, August 1975-October 1979 (Box 31, Folder 2)
      Articles about the creation of new towns Burke Center and Franklin, Virginia.
    - Chronology Notes, Undated (Box 31, Folder 3)
      Notes about the chronology of Til Hazel's life.
    - Taxpayers, May 1991 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      An article about Til Hazel and development in Northern Virginia.
    - Bill Hazel, February 1987 (Box 31, Folder 5)
      An article about Til Hazel's brother, Bill.
    - Thomas and Fiske, 1979-1984 (Box 31, Folder 6)
      Lists and descriptions of Virginia lawyers.
    - Ed Risse, October 1988 (Box 31, Folder 7)
      Notes about Ed Risse.
    - Bio, January-May 1988 (Box 31, Folder 8)
      Notes and an article about the life and times of Til Hazel.
    - Outer Beltway, Undated (Box 31, Folder 9)
      An article about Jack Herrity and Til Hazel.
    - Outrages, October 1964-June 1979 (Box 31, Folder 10)
      Articles about Til Hazel's professional actions in Northern Virginia.
    - Bribery Case, September 1966-April 1975 (Box 31, Folder 11)
      Notes and articles about a corruption trial in which Til Hazel participated.
    - Fact Check 11/11/90 Til Hazel, October 1988-November 1990 (Box 31, Folder 12)
      Notes and articles about Til Hazel and information about the Tenth Congressional District. Also included is a rough draft of part 4 of chapter ten of "Edge City"
    - Fairfax Symphony Board of Directors, 1988-1989 (Box 31, Folder 13)
      A contact list of the Fairfax Symphony Board of Directors.
    - Til Transcript, February 1989 (Box 31, Folder 14)
      Transcript of an interview between Garreau and Til Hazel.
    - Til Hazel, October 1988-December 1990 (Box 31, Folder 15)
      Notes and newspaper articles about Til Hazel's work in land preservation.
    - Harvard Magazine, September-October 1985 (Box 31, Folder 16)
      The September-October 1985 issue of Harvard Magazine.
    - MILT Peterson (Til Notes), December 1988-January 1989 (Box 31, Folder 17)
      Notes about Til Hazel.
    - The Hazel Printouts/Interview Notes, December 1988-September 1989 (Box 31, Folder 18)
      Notes from and a transcript of a Til Hazel interview and a Virginia Business article about Til Hazel.
    - Til Hazel's Office, Undated (Box 31, Folder 19)
      Notes about Til Hazel's office.
    - Til Hazel Transcripts, July-September 1989 (Box 32, Folder 1)
      Transcripts from interviews between Garreau and Til Hazel.
    - Huntley Hall, Undated (Box 32, Folder 2)
      An invitation from Til Hazel to an event at his house.
    - John Harris Piece, September 1988 (Box 32, Folder 3)
      An article about Til Hazel by John Harris.
    - Flint Hill, December 1989 (Box 32, Folder 4)
      Articles about Flint Hill prep school and the Virginia gubernatorial race.
    - Interview An Evening At Huntley Hall, June 1987-September 1988 (Box 32, Folder 5)
      Articles, a press release, notes and interview questions about and for Til Hazel.
    - Interviews News Virginia, October 1987-October 1988 (Box 32, Folder 6)
      Articles about Til Hazel.
  - Subseries 1.3: Land Preservation, September 1990-November 1991
    Materials from Joel Garreau's book "Edge City" dealing with Land Preservation. As edge cities grew in areas such as Northern Virginia, development threatened land that held significant historical value, such as the Civil War battlefield at Manassas. There was much controversy over the proposed construction of a shopping complex within the borders of Manassas National Battlefield Park.
    - Manassas National Battlefield Park, January-August 1988 (Box 32, Folder 7)
      Newspaper articles about the proposed construction of a shopping complex in Manassas National Battlefield Park.
    - Save The Battlefield Coalition, Inc., August-October 1991 (Box 32, Folder 8)
      Correspondence, surveys, articles, brochures and personnel profiles from the Save The Battlefield Coalition, Inc.
    - Manassas Sources, April 1989-October 1991 (Box 32, Folder 9)
      Correspondence and a magazine about preservation.
    - National Trust for Historic Preservation, June 1990 (Box 32, Folder 10)
      Correspondence, meeting schedules, a list of participants and contact information for a National Trust for Historic Preservation roundtable meeting.
    - Manassas, January 1989 (Box 32, Folder 11)
      Notes, contact information and an article about Manassas.
    - Manassas Battlefield, May 1969-November 1991 (Box 32, Folder 12)
      Notes, articles, newsletters, pamphlets and correspondence about the preservation of Manassas Battlefield.
    - Manassas Tersh Boasberg, December 1988 (Box 32, Folder 13)
      Tersh Boasberg's Curriculum Vitae.
    - Victory Party Manassas, December 1988 (Box 32, Folder 14)
      A notebook from the final victory party at Manassas Battlefield.
    - William Center-Manassas Battleground, November 1986-November 1988 (Box 32, Folder 15)
      Articles, notes and transcripts of articles about the construction of the Williams Center, a shopping complex.
    - Annie's Handouts, May-July 1988 (Box 32, Folder 16)
      Preservation newsletters, articles and a fact sheet about the Manassas Battlefield dispute.
    - Manassas Flap-Lynda McCarthy, February 1988 (Box 32, Folder 17)
      A publication about the opening of an exhibit at the CIA called "Blacks in the Military".
    - Manassas Flap, September 1967-October 1990 (Box 32, Folder 18)
      Articles about Ken Burns' Civil War documentary and preserving Manassas Battlefield.
    - The Land Dispute, April 1990-June 1990 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      Articles about land preservation.
    - The Land, May 1981-August 1990 (Box 33, Folder 2 (Oversize Box 65))
      Correspondence, press releases, notes, articles, essays, speech transcripts, a list of panelists, charts, graphs, a book excerpt and a magazine about land preservation. OVERSIZE BOX 65
    - Land Preservation, July 1990-August 1991 (Box 33, Folder 3)
      Articles and correspondence about a land gift of 100,000 to the United States.
    - Brandy Station Foundation Bulletin, October 1991 (Box 33, Folder 4)
      Three issues of the Brandy Station Foundation Bulletin. Problems/Solutions
  - Subseries 1.4: History, 1970-October 1990
    Historical background material for Joel Garreau's "Edge City". Material covers the American Civil War, Henry Adams, Daniel Boone, Thomas Jefferson, Jamestown, Pleasant Vale Baptist Church, Leesburg, Shenandoah Valley, Pierre L'Enfant, Washington, DC, and Virginia.
    - Civil War, October 1990 (Box 33, Folder 5)
      The October 8, 1990 issue of Newsweek magazine, featuring an article about Ken Burns' documentary The Civil War.
    - Henry Adams, Undated (Box 33, Folder 6)
      Chapter 25 from "The Education of Henry Adams".
    - Daniel Boone, Undated (Box 33, Folder 7)
      An article about Daniel Boone.
    - Civil War, August 1988-June 1989 (Box 33, Folder 8)
      Articles about the Civil War and land development.
    - Thomas Jefferson, Undated (Box 33, Folder 9)
      Notes taken from Thomas Jefferson's book "Notes on The State of Virginia".
    - Jamestown, November 1988 (Box 33, Folder 10)
      Articles and two excerpts from books about settlers in Jamestown, Virginia.
    - Jefferson UVA, 1987 (Box 33, Folder 11)
      Articles and documents about Thomas Jefferson's relationship with the University of Virginia.
    - Pleasant Vale Baptist Church, June 1987 (Box 33, Folder 12)
      An article about the restoration of a Baptist Church in Fauquier County, Virginia.
    - Leesburg Shenandoah Valley, November 1988 (Box 33, Folder 13)
      Articles and correspondence about a historical architecture tour of Virginia.
    - Pierre L'Enfant, January 1990 (Box 33, Folder 14)
      An article about Pierre Charles L'Enfant and his design of Washington.
    - Washington, DC, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 15)
      "Some Present-Minded Thoughts on the History of Washington, D.C." by Atlee E. Shidler.
    - Virginia History, September-October 1990 (Box 33, Folder 16)
      Articles about Virginia history.
  - Subseries 1.5: Race/Poverty, July 1982-August 1992
    Material from Joel Garreau's files dealing with race and poverty.
    - Blacks Los Angeles, Blacks Middle Class Growth, Poverty AFDC Stats, September 1986-April 1990 (Box 33, Folder 17)
      Articles about the changing economic situation of African Americans in America. Also included is "According to Age: Longitudinal Profiles of AFDC Recipients and the Poor by Age Group" by Charles Murray.
    - Black Underclass, December 1988-March 1990 (Box 33, Folder 18)
      Articles, correspondence, press release and a pamphlet about lower class African Americans. Also included are three books about poverty in Washington, DC.
    - Henry L Gates Black Scholar, March 1985-April 1990 (Box 33, Folder 19)
      Notes, correspondence, data tables and articles about Henry L. Gates. Also included is "Marital Status and Living Arrangements: March 1985".
    - Poverty Status of Families, 1982-1985 (Box 33, Folder 20)
      Documents about income, poverty status and families from the US Department of Commerce.
    - Poverty of Families, April 1984-January 1990 (Box 33, Folder 21)
      Articles, notes, press releases and data highlights about poverties and families. Also included is "Educational Background and Economic Status: Spring 1984".
    - Notebooks, Undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
      Notebooks and notebook pages from Atlanta.
    - Cowart Lake Ventures, October 1989-March 1990 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      Documents about development projects in the Atlanta, Georgia area.
    - The Martin Luther King, Jr. Center, 1987-1990 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      A listing of programs, correspondence, contact information and notes from the Martin Luther King, Jr. Center.
    - Blacks in the Suburbs, February 1988-December 1989 (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Articles, notes, correspondence and essays about African Americans in the suburbs.
    - Blacks Cluster, March-April 1990 (Box 34, Folder 5)
      Articles, notes and real estate market reports about enclaves and African American communities
    - Urban Structure-Dana F. White, July-October 1982 (Box 34, Folder 6)
      "The Black Sides of Atlanta: A Geography of Expansion and Containment, 1970-1870" by Dana F. White.
    - Chapter 5 Atlanta, October 1987-February 1988 (Box 34, Folder 7)
      Material used for chapter 5 about Atlanta, Georgia from Garreau's book "Edge City". Material includes notebooks, articles, maps, company profiles, fact sheets, contact information, promotional material, notes, magazines, restaurant menus, travel itineraries, plane tickets and other information about the Atlanta area and a building complex called Buckhead.
    - South DeKalb, March 1990 (Box 34, Folder 8)
      An article about a community day in South DeKalb, Georgia.
    - Perimeter Center, Atlanta, December 1986-June 1990 (Box 34, Folder 9)
      Articles, charts, graphs, maps and promotional material about a commercial development building called the Perimeter Center. Also included is an issue of Development Magazine.
    - Blacks Local Middle Class, May 1987-September 1989 (Box 35, Folder 1)
      Notes, articles and correspondence about the growth of Atlanta and it's suburbs.
    - Notes Atlanta, Undated (Box 35, Folder 2)
      Notes and contact information about Atlanta, Georgia.
    - Forsythe County Egalitarianism, January 1989 (Box 35, Folder 3)
      Two articles about Forsythe County, Georgia and egalitarianism.
    - Michael Lomax John Lewis, August 1982-March 1990 (Box 35, Folder 4)
      A transcript of an interview between Garreau and Michael Lomax, a tribute to Congressman John Lewis, and congressional district maps of Fulton and DeKalb Counties in Georgia.
    - 1988 Household Income Stats, Ebenezer Baptist Church, October 1987-April 1990 (Box 35, Folder 5)
      Articles about the reconstruction of Atlanta, Georgia after the civil war, race and remembering the Civil War, programs from church services at Ebenezer Baptist Church and the 1988 Household Income Report from the Atlanta Regional Commission.
    - Bart Landry Notes, MSA Levels, Black Atlanta Photobook, August 1989-January 1990 (Box 35, Folder 6)
      Data tables of MSA Levels, correspondence, notes about Bart Landry and "Scenes of Black Atlanta".
    - LA Blacks, Biracial Politics Kotkin, January 1990 (Box 35, Folder 7)
      "New Interethnic Conflict Replaces an L.A. History of Biracial Politics" by Joel Kotkin.
    - Jews and Blacks, April 1990 (Box 35, Folder 8)
      An article about Jewish people in Atlanta, Georgia.
    - Black Newspapers, March 1990 (Box 35, Folder 9)
      An issue of the Atlanta News Weekly and an issue of the Atlanta Courier Journal.
    - Recommended Readings Nathan McCall Notes, August 1989-May 1990 (Box 35, Folder 10)
      Notes and articles about segregation and Nathan McCall
    - Ernie Dirico Notes, April 1990 (Box 35, Folder 11)
      Notes and a message to Garreau from Ernie Dirico
    - Black Flight, March 1990 (Box 35, Folder 12)
      An article about the migration of African Americans out of the cities.
    - Cobb County Clips, April 1990 (Box 35, Folder 13)
      Articles about African Americans in Cobb County, Georgia.
    - Affluent Blacks, November 1989 (Box 35, Folder 14)
      An article about African Americans who earn more than 50,000 dollars a year.
    - Southern Christian Leadership Conference, May 1988-February 1989 (Box 35, Folder 15)
      Notes and articles about discrimination against African Americans.
    - Southern Christian Leadership Conference, April 1990 (Box 35, Folder 16)
      Fliers from the Southern Christian Leadership Conference promoting events in observance of the anniversary of the assassination of Martin Luther King, Jr.
    - Southern Regional Council Bulletins, July 1988-December 1989 (Box 35, Folder 17)
      Five issues of Southern Changes, a newsletter from The Southern Regional Council.